[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
more people will be trickling in so
welcome to the stoa um i'm peter limberg
the steward of the stoa
and the stow is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge of this very
moment
and today we have bio i come olafe
bio is a lecturer speaker author father
from what i see an all-around awesome
guy and
people have been recommending um bio to
come on to stoa since the store
first started really about five months
ago and it was
only until uh maria clara who's a
facilitator at the
stoa um came to the store and we watched
some of her videos
uh with interviews with bio and i'm like
man
this guy i gotta get this guy in the
store i gotta talk to this guy just
though he has such a um
as you'll soon see he sets your way with
words
um so that being said i emailed the uh
bio and said hey would you like to come
on the podcast or the this communal
podcast that we have here at the stoa
uh he was excited to do so i said
there's anything you want to talk about
and uh he just like just dropped this
poetic title
and i'm like okay i get done and this is
what he said to me in the email
i thought we could discuss the weirdness
of these times
the archetypal longings for answers uh
as we face
unprecedented series of upheavals and
challenges to settler epistemologies
and the promise in the figure of the
fugitive
so done i'm excited uh to have this
conversation so how it's going to go um
about now we'll chat back and forth if
you have any questions
i just start dropping them in the the
chat box right now
and then if you haven't been here before
i call on you you'll meet yourself ask
your question if you don't want to be on
youtube this will eventually go on
youtube
just indicate that in the um the chats
and i will
um read it on your path so that being
said
i will uh allow bio to
meet himself and uh how's it going my
friend
hello hello hello hello hello uh
brothers and sisters how you guys doing
um peter thank you for inviting me here
thank you
it's good to be here it's a pleasure to
have you um
so now am i supposed to start my stuff
well i i can launch you off with um yeah
please swing the question yeah
i'll throw that um so why the title
uh the title of today's talk um and then
that question
that you had in it i think i was high
when i wrote that title to you
i was high when i wrote it too exactly
so i cannot remember right to that title
i probably was having a lot of guidos or
something
but i um i recall the question
and the question lives with me and i
think it lives with most of us
um where is god now now that that is not
supposed to be
uh a theological question
uh that is reducible to
questions about uh whether god exists or
not or which god you're talking about
i'm not religious myself i'm a
recovering christian
as well as a recovering psychologist i'm
recovering from a lot of things by the
way
um so that's just to warn you guys
but it's a deeper question than
than how it presents itself but let me
start
how rude of me um to greet you all first
and to to say i hope you're well
wherever you are in the world
um my name is bayo akomalafe
i'm from the europa people in nigeria
which is west of wakanda if you
if you know where that is nerds joke
um it works most of the time and um i
live here in india
though my wife is indian my family is
indian and i'm making my life and living
here
in intimate small moments asking
profound questions and ordinary
questions like where is god now
especially in a time such as we're in
right now in the pandemic
um but brother to answer that question
and i don't think i can even pretend to
answer it um most of us have a sense of
that we're facing something beyond
our ability to respond to
that's something mysterious something
really powerful
has descended if you will and
and that to even
suppose that we can answer it with a
vaccine
or we can just dismiss it with a new
policy
or a mask or something is to proliferate
the
and triple centricity the idea that we
are at the center of the universe
we're in charge of things and there's a
sense of despair that we're feeling
today
not just despair we're feeling the sense
of grief and loss
and humility it's like a tiny critter
a tiny virus whatever it is you know
brought us down to earth
so we're coming down to earth um and
we're in a place where we're
in maybe small doses we're being
defeated
and that is a beautiful gift to be
defeated over and over again
but i i saw this uh just by way of
lengthening this conversation i i saw
this
article here in india in a newspaper
that some women in kerala
which is a state in here in india
had mounted an altar
to worship the corona goddess
the corona goddess and they mounted this
altar
on the beach you know and decorated and
ordained and anointed this altar with
sweets
and biscuits and stuff and wrappings
and they worship the corona goddess and
i started to think about
um this is where that question i think
came from one of the
sources of it i started to think about
how we're responding
to this crisis i i'm known for saying
over and over again that the way we
respond to the crisis
is part of the crisis that we are
wrapped
up in cycles of responsivity um
which can get very toxic because
sometimes we respond even in anger
you know with a sense of outrage and
justice seeking
we might tend we tend to proliferate or
reinforce the very conditions that we're
trying to leave behind
just like maybe an ant in a bowl of milk
curdling the milk in the very attempt to
crawl out
of the bowl of milk um so i started to
think about
this perverse queer strange
act of responding to a pandemic by
treating it as a being as a
as something ethereal as a goddess if
you as something archetypal
and then that led me to james hillman
who is uh
a famous archetypal psychologist i think
would hate to refer to himself he's late
now
as the founder of archetypal psychology
but
one of the axiomatic statements of that
field
is that the gods never left
modernity is the cons is the is the
i don't i don't like to use the word
illusion but it's the notion that the
world is flat
that uh we live in a world that is
entirely or almost entirely
of our making right that such
passe notions like gods and goddesses
and myths should be relegated to the
the the backwaters of history we
shouldn't talk about
stuff like baldur or loki or issue
or ludomari we shouldn't talk about
those things
because we're now sophisticated you see
we have technology you see
we're rational you see um but the idea
that
the psyche what we call the psyche is
not in the mind
but is ecological that we are
um uh we are
beyond uh not we i mean the world
is beyond uh just the mind
that is in the skull so to speak that we
are
larger than our frames of thinking our
concepts how we spill through containers
and so the archetypes that i have always
been part of our imaginations
are still alive that in a table a god is
there
you know that in a pen or in a zoom
conversation
there's a god lingering nearby there's a
neighborhood
of gods a pantheon of beings that we do
not know how to recognize
that is lurking like stowaways in the
ordinary
that the ordinary is what the
extraordinary seeks to become
actually that we are already
here right now in a thick middle that is
thick with
different kinds of bodies that we do not
even
uh have names for that idea is
is strong in this question that i ask
where is god now
because right now we are in a fix we're
in a mess
as a people as a species and there is no
saying where where things might lead
and i i have a sense that maybe
um this is the time for us to call to
question
the ideas of god that we've been dealing
with
the notion of god as some some something
transcendent
um seems uh antiquated to me
or no longer strategically useful right
now
i think we have to deal with a god that
is imminent
and a god that is here hiding in the
ordinary
enchanting the ordinary inviting us to
do some other kind of work
that reshapes ourselves what am i trying
to say
um i framed this uh this conversation as
an exploration of theo politics now that
might seem
um crazy to some people uh theology is
something apart from politics politics
is down to earth theology is
a consideration of beings that have
beards and look like gandalf or
something that is outside of our bubbles
of
you know interaction um and yet
when i think of a theopolitics and i
don't know that i've seen
that word used before i just matched
together like i said i was high
um a theopolitics is a consideration of
how we've been shaped
by an image of god how archetypes are
lingering in the ways we respond to
crisis
and how we are part of fields of
action and engagement now we might think
of ourselves as
free you know liberal humanism is this
idea
that we are free that we make choices
here
uh that we decide of course we should
take all that we want is political will
and resources
but now we are now learning and
reckoning with the idea with the notion
the invitation that we are not free at
all we are indebted
to the world a world that is not made of
things but made of relationships
that is in a sense we're still attached
to a god of the plantation
and here i'm bringing in the trope of
slavery we're still attached to a god
that proliferates certain kinds of
realities
certain kinds of politics certain kinds
of dualisms
that will keep us trapped in a pandemic
thinking that
the only thing to do about it is to
defeat it it's an enemy
right all we need to do is come up with
a vaccine and we're gone
and we're home free um but i feel this
time just like those women in kerala
is a time for us to revisit the gods we
worship
again i'm not speaking religiously i'm
speaking in a different
sense right now all of us are
worshipping a god of the plantation in a
sense
when we attend a zoom conversation when
we pick up our phones
we're activating algorithms and
computational logics
that move beyond our human bodies and
that
shape the way we think about the world
approach it
respond to it think about it act within
it
i feel there are other spaces of power
that we can dwell in
and the only way to get there is to
become fugitive
is to learn how to listen to and worship
with the trickster
is to learn about the god that is hiding
in the shadows
and not the gods of regimes of light
that dwells
above the fray if you will we're being
invited i feel to
to lose our way my people back in
nigeria would say in order to find your
way
you must learn to lose it what kind of
god will allow us to
lose our way what kind of god will allow
us to spill
what kind of god will allow us to lose
the coherence of the image
you know the christian text says we're
made in the image of god
the bible were made in the image of god
and i just want to point out
that the image you know how we think
about images today
it's changing right now you're all
thumbnails on my screen
um images on my screen
however um we now know that images are
not just photographic
um artifacts or items that represent an
objective reality images
are algorithms images are programs
themselves
um so they're not just uh stable
realities
they're things that are constantly
changing they're programs they're not
just the results of programs
your programs in themselves i feel that
the image
of god needs to be composted today now
it feels like uh
it may feel like something um totally
outside of the conversation about
pandemics
and racism and the anthropocene and
climate chaos
and ecocide to talk about composting god
but i feel maybe that's what we need to
be doing today
moving outside of the intelligible
finding
the spaces of not knowing dwelling in
the places
of wounds and cracks in our bodies and
noticing that that's where
we need to change that's where we need
to shape shift
it's the trickster's call that beckons
that we need to heed right now the
trickster invites us to move outside of
the plantation that proliferates the
familia
the trickster invites us to fall apart
so that we can be made in different ways
um i'm exploring this and i i want to
stop here i'm exploring this in terms of
the idea of making sanctuary
in the in the in the terms of uh um
losing our flesh and becoming different
kinds of
um composed flesh if you will but let's
let's let's hold it there for now
so uh again uh just drop your questions
in the chat uh
um then i'll call on youtube yourself so
it came to mind when you're talking a
bunch of things
uh so one of them is like the how do i
go to war with this old god
you know like then like rally the the
the
the armor the weapons and all that type
of stuff and i'm like
that is not the mindset that uh you're
encouraging right now um
yeah so what like
and this this a lot of the space that we
geek out here in the store we talk about
psycho technologies like whether it's
meditation or
uh writing practices or breath work
something that kind of transforms
our own individual perception of the
world
and ourselves what kind of
psychotechnologies that would help us
compost god hmm
um i would i would offer this
term i call it feel faji
and that literally means eating god um
from the term am triple fragic which is
somewhat similar to cannibalism but it's
not quite
cannibalism um i think there is
there is room for eating god speaking
mystically
for us to take the flesh eat and become
something really different i wouldn't
reduce it to um
so what i hear in your question about
psychotechnologies
is i don't want people to hear from that
psychedelia or or
certain practices that invite us to go
inward
i would i would think of it as an
ecological principle
as an ecological invitation as something
irreducibly communitarian
or minoritarian as a different kind of
politics that might be weird
that is not about composing new subjects
that attend to power
that attend to the status quo
but is about inviting an entirely
different framework of
acting and engaging with the planet um
that basically um that basically strips
apart the very foundations of
man or the human um and let me take that
even further
i think the human when we talk about the
human we imagine the bipedal things that
we
are you know heads hands and stuff
but but i feel that the human is more
than that the human is an assemblage of
bodies
the human is a colonial imperial
force um that enlists
different kinds of ideas and concepts in
order to concretize itself
i also think of the human as whiteness
not white identified bodies
but whiteness whiteness is this order
this flattening of the world
this this uh dismissal of archetypes of
gods and goddesses
in order to impose a rational order
where the stability of the individual
is assured basically it's like again
like a flattening of worlds
and i mean this not in metaphorical
terms i mean the literal
excavation of plat of of of land i mean
the displacement of people
i mean leveling trees in order to build
a parking lot
this is the paradigm of man this is the
paradigm of whiteness
that enlists white identified bodies
black identified bodies
humans and non-humans are like ideas and
concepts
in order to propagate an age or a
paradigm of the self
okay um so when you talk about
technologies these technologies i'm
looking for
are fugitive technologies technologies
that
invite fugitive incapacitation that help
us unlearn
mastery that help us lose our way and it
might bring in psychedelics
it might bring in different ways of
telling stories it might bring in a
cartographical project
that is about going into the world and
finding new ways of doing research
it might invite post-qualitative
research to speak in academic terms
uh that in that invite us to listen to
plants
to bring in the data from people who
have been there before
who know how to listen to the world
without codifying categorizing and
indexing it and putting it in the
academic bubble
we need to lose our way is what i'm
trying to say and it might start to the
perverse
with the spark of the perverse like uh
women and kerala
are worshiping the corona goddess
instead of dismissing that news
we want to lean in further and say what
kinds of places
are we being invited to go to you know
with this invitation to worship a virus
um instead of just dismissing it as an
enemy
you know that that's where the spark is
and i feel most of us might be sensing
that even right now
um we might be feeling
awkward like um the questions we know
how to ask are no longer possible
or the ways we have organized our lives
are no longer possible
for instance in india here uh newspapers
are
filled with headlines about what do we
do with our kids now they're not going
to school
you know uh where do what do we do with
them
if we can't send them to school what is
education then
if it's going to be held on you know in
zoom sessions
my wife and i have been on schooling our
children since they were born
we've never sent them to school instead
we see them as part of the world
as elders my wife has a name for her she
calls it transparenting
where we learn with our kids we treat
them as philosophers even though they
don't have phds like us
and then we embark on research journeys
to learn through their eyes
that's a psychotechnology that's a
modest
modest artifact in the altar of
offerings in the constellation of
offerings
that might help us find our way to
potentially wiser
economies potentially wiser worlds
but i want to um centralize here at the
concept of the human
what gets in our way is to human what
gets in our way is this
imperial order that says everything
outside of the rational
everything outside of your way of
thinking is the enemy get rid of it so
you can get ahead um yeah
that's the that's the trouble right
and uh you know a lot of these
metamodern integral spaces
they talk about yes ending like you know
you yes end the previous paradigm or
take the
the best out of it um like
before we become like complete fugitives
is there anything we could learn or gain
from the old gods
i like that so we don't want to
absolutely stuff right and say
um um
that uh and let me put it this way that
i've been saying for instance that even
whiteness is not evil
you know many writers will speak about
getting rid
of whiteness um and
dismantling it well i want to dismantle
it
i want a situation where many kinds of
bodies can thrive
but at the same time the moment i
displace
or treat whiteness as an evil then i let
it slip away from analysis
then i let it become something entirely
different then it's no longer of this
world
um so i really appreciate you noticing
that um
the gods were leaving behind they are
not necessarily evil
or none that's we're not abandoning them
if you will
while in a relational universe in a
universe that is built on relationship
and entanglements abandonment is not
possible
i describe myself as a recovering
christian
but even then i i cannot i haven't
abandoned things that are still living
with me
and in me right so
we don't want to a different kind of
politics a politics that
invites us to become animal to become
invisible
we don't want to say that this replaces
this we don't want to say that this is a
a progress narrative that displaces a
dinosaur kind of thinking that we're
leaving behind
what kinds of lessons can we learn about
um the old gods i don't know for now
brother
i all i can say is maybe we can learn
lessons
and it's just holding that space of
learning from the old gods
is just as vital to me as knowing the
questions themselves
beautiful yeah so let's uh
turn to some questions oliver king you
had a question if you cannot mute
yourself
hey peter hey bio um so my question
is regarding you know to extend some of
the
ideas that have been brought up is like
theophage right eating gods
or dining on the armor and going to war
with these old gods
and these are perhaps extensions
like a marvel cinematic uh
thing right sorry no no it's okay
um so perhaps necessarily these feel
like artifacts of anthropoceneic
ways of thinking and
we keep relating ourselves in different
ways of these gods both old
and potentially new but there are also
people who
are not yet ready to leave the altars
upon which they've already become
frustrated
um god or new so
do you have any idea or suggestion
or narrative about how
maybe not we should but how we can
relate to these people
in healthy and constructive ways how we
can persuade people
no just relate to them in healthy income
oh relate to them
okay okay i didn't hear them
well i'm not in the uh in the business
of um and and i know this know what you
asked
um i'm not in the business of
evangelizing
like the world is too complex too
promiscuous to be reduced to any one way
of thinking about it
um so so i i'm very very
hesitant to to impose one way of
thinking about things
i only invite here and ethology
and ethics not morality here morality is
transcendent
speaking about ethics as imminent i am
alive to different ways of behaving
um with the world around us um
and it will not appeal to people in
it will not land with everyone
everywhere the same way
right and i'm fine with that if if
both of us oliver brother if if we could
find
words to say sentences to construct that
will immediately change views around the
world
i would i would not say those words
because i would not want to live in a
universe
where everyone could be persuaded in the
same way i think truth
is reductionistic i think truth gets in
the way of the expansion
of the amazing complexity that is
life so that to speak about it is to
lose
something is to miss a spot somewhere um
and i don't know if i'm just riffing
here
yeah like i said um there are lots of
things there are foot around me
but i want to say that um the way i
relate to this
is to invite is to invite a different
um way of relating with the world a
different kind of inquiry
that might bring a collective together
to ask different kinds of questions to
compile
um different kinds of underground
spiritual technologies
if you will um which we might
constellate in order to lose our way
again i don't want to i'm not speaking
poetically here when i speak about
losing one's way
i've actually sat with healers and
shamans
that will basically say the same thing
that what we need to do is to
stray out of the ecology that
proliferates the familiar
um we need to stray out of there and the
only way to do this
is not to resist and i'm not trying to
put down resistance we need resistance
we need critique-based feminisms we need
all of that
but critique can only take us so far
we need other places of power otherwise
and not everyone will find a way there
it's not the next brother
this is not the next beautiful world
this is not a manifesto this is not a
utopian
this is not some kind of aquarian age
stuff i'm talking about
i'm just speaking about the modest
openings the fugitive cracks in the
bubble of thinking
that might open up and where we might
find a way of being alive with the world
you know this is really historical stuff
here
i do you know anything about brazil and
the killembollas and the favelas
uh learn about that history for instance
how they
how they snuck out you know and built
villages
had different ways of thinking about the
world had different ways of thinking
about children and schools and stuff
you know i feel that is what we've been
invited to now because i'm really
tired of the [ __ ] stuff you know
that says oh all we need to do is just
build a manifesto
i'm i'm a citizen of the so-called
global south and the passive recipient
of the good intentions of the west you
know
many people come and say all we need to
do is just do this we have the ideas
down
we just need you guys to work it out
and it we end up repeating it
this reinforcing the same things we're
trying to leave behind so what do you do
when you're stuck in a cycle of
repeatability
my suggestion is we need to fall apart
we can we can find new ways of grieving
together and i'm not just talking about
crying together
we can treat grief as activism we can
instead of
talking about climate justice all the
time what if you know we fall off the
highway of climate justice and we find
other concepts like climate saudaji so
that is the word from brazil
which is about nostalgia which is about
looking at loss and staying with loss
where are the places of power in
hopelessness
you know um so solutions will not always
get us there in fact there are hidden
costs to solutions
that we need to stay with and maybe my
invitation there is
um i call it post activism uh what you
do at the end of a world
is not to try to build a new one
immediately
is to try to know the one you're in
right now
uh to stay with the alienness of it and
to listen to it
and i think we're in an alien world
right now with the pandemic with george
floyd
um with the antropol scene we're in an
alien world
unlike anything we've been in before
it's an advent
you know and now we need to do the work
of falling apart
awesome okay um another question from
ireland i think uh
elon you had a question above
hi hi hi hi bio
i saw you last year in victoria so good
to be
in commercial
yeah um so i love that term you use
around
composting i was working at a farm the
other day and we built a huge compost it
actually looked like a burial mound when
it was done
and just how um
nothing gets wasted in that process
but what i was wondering in
as we sort of consider all the
all that we've been uh living with that
maybe now
we want to discard what
what belongs on the compost heap what
actually
we just want to burn and put in the
garbage
and what goes on the altar and i'm
almost like is that
an experiment we do like how do i
approach if i
if i put that politician that just
i find so much frustration and concern
around
you know like what if i put them on the
altar instead of right to the refuse
uh so i just say our approach
of the problems we seem to be facing
um how to how to kind of know
or is it all just we're in a big
experiment and we're trying new things
right thank you sister uh
uh what if the compost heap
is the altar ah and and and what if
and what if the um and what if it's not
us you know that is it's not us in
charge of decorating this altar
you know um the altar is alive in its
own right
it is assembling its the uh its
worshippers if you will
it's religiously heavy language i know
worshipers worship but i
titled this theo politics so what do you
know what do you do
um and and my sense here is
here's here's a story from from the from
the bible i feel like this is church
where jacob is running from
his brother he's usurped the
[Music]
the birthright of his elder brother esau
and esau is hot on his tail
and jacob is known as a trickster
he's a con man you know he's just
sleazed his way through stuff
and so he finds himself in a place of
desperation
in this wilderness place and he doesn't
know where to go
he's sent his large family the entourage
to a different part of the country
and he's really like yeah i don't know
what to do my brother is going to kill
me for the sin i committed
all those years ago and things get
strange he's sleeping
in the middle of the night some guy just
stands on top of him
and starts to beat him up and they start
to wrestle
if you guys don't i'm looking at faces
if you guys don't know this story you're
all going to hell
by the way you're all going to hell
you haven't been going to church um i
kid
and uh and this they just start
wrestling and he realizes in the
in the middle of the struggle that he's
fighting god
he's he's fighting his fighting god
himself
and then he says you know dude
i'm not sure he said dude but he like
i'm not gonna let you go
until you bless me i'm not gonna let you
go until you bless me
and god proceeds to bless him a
queer blessing this is because god
proceeds to
smite his using biblical language king
jamesian language
to smite his thigh and to dislocate the
joint
so so that he cannot walk
anymore and then god renames him
says your name shall no longer be jacob
you know
you shall now be called israel um
and i've always wondered why a blessing
would be a punch
to to the body like a wound to the body
and maybe maybe that's the consideration
here
um the opening is the wound uh
the the place where we are defeated is
the invitation
that's the iv that's the rsvp there it's
like
the world reminds us in in
poetic in archetypal in philosophical
in spiritual in social ways to
trace out the tentacularities of our
bodies
again and again that we're not as
coherent intelligible articulate as we
think we are
as our politics presupposes we are
whether it's identity politics or
trumpian politics
that we're not as articulate or as
coherent as
or as intelligible we're unwieldy we're
diffracted
and so small opportunities come openings
come that allow us to touch our bodies
to trace
um one very real sense that is happening
is
ancestral dna tests as uh capitalist as
that might sound
but yes even right there in that really
capitalist enterprise
is the opening that maybe identity is
something
more perverse than the boxes we take
when we fill census forms
that um that black is not
coherently black um that white
is already lingering you know with
with the not white and that we're mixed
up
and we're messed up you know in ways
that our politics does not know how to
deal with
um so i feel this is an opportunity you
might call it a portal you might call it
an opportunity you might call it
um an opening in the sky a crack in the
ground a rupture
in place of a rapture but there is
there is the invitation and it's not us
in charge
we can only sniff it out we can use
historical figures of the slave ship
you know i spoke about the slave ship
when we met in victoria
um of the slave ship as a model
you know those souls that were in those
slave ships
gave us an aesthetic a cultural
aesthetic or tool or technology what my
brother here is calling a psycho
technology
of of using fugitive ways of
creatively responding to oppression you
know
they found ways of using grief to hold
their gods
and those gods have now multiplied in
the so-called new world in brazil and
cuba in jamaica
in hip-hop in washington dc for you guys
who are living in that area
um the phallic structure i don't know
what it's called you know that phallic
structure
in the dc monument what's it called the
washington
uh thing there is actually um
stolen stolen pilfered from
ancient kemet in which is the old name
for egypt
um which is also a manifestation of a
euroba
god called issue this guy right here
issue so so that when you mount those
altars and you think
dare to the gods of rationality the
fugitives have already
snuck in the immigrants
immigrant deities are hiding right there
in the white house
and we don't know how to deal with that
so in times when rationality falls open
when our ways are making sense our
collective sense making a paradigm
you know it is broken then we have an
invitation
and then the compost heap calls those
and i'm not talking about some kind of
elite class but it brings to the wounded
close
and then they become beacons further
invitations for further brokenness
you know a different kind of politics
that might
proliferate sorry i'm going on an honor
any follow-up there um
no that's plenty to just try and
absorb compost thank you
yeah nicholas benjamin you had a
question
thank you peter and thank you bio this
is one of the most
flexible ontological models that i've
come across
and enrich and it's just coming out of
nowhere and exploding
all ways of seeing and i'm so excited to
have discovered your work it's the
dosa that i took the guidosa the
highness
so so um my question for you is
so i i'm i'm right now i'm currently
reading um a thousand plateaus
by by donors it's like instruction
manual for seeing the world in a
different way
and it sounds to me like in much the
same way you were describing
a set of models and mechanisms and
machines and
ontological moves that are that are so
rich and
new that together they could combine to
form this kind of a compass for seeking
out fugitivity
in in modernity and exploring and
expanding those cracks
for us to achieve a breakout to
reach an outside it's almost like a
gracious move
but not in the right accelerations to it
so my but my question is
it also sounds like you were asking us
to revere
defeatism to what revered defeatism
being defeated yeah yeah being defeated
yeah and um i worry that that is
that that ask is dead in the water for
anybody who has skin in the game of the
crew
and and so i'm also worried that your
your
your lens will die on on the hill of
critique
as so many other you know anti-hegemonic
moves have done yeah so in what way
can this be deployed and what way can we
do the ontological bridge work to
generate allies faster than we alienate
the future right right thank you brother
i i didn't get everything you said i'm
having problems with my
sound i'm sure you can help me hear me
well um
but i try and respond to what i think i
i i heard and and correct me if i
you can put it on the chat maybe i'll
just uh okay i'm having some problems
with my
sound um but what i heard is
something that you know
that if you think it's dead in the water
to
to to seek defeat something like that
that
that a politics that is premised on
defeat may not be appealing to
to allies and potential allies okay good
awesome
great um three chinese curses
i curse you with my brother um
it's apocryphal meaning of course that
it
i i no one that i know can verify
the historical accuracy of these words
i'm about to share with you
but i've heard that um
there are three curses um came from
down back in the day in china
the first one and it increases in
potency as you go down the line
the first one is may you live in
interesting times that's the first curse
and i think we're all in very very very
interesting times right
the second one is may you be seen by the
emperor
may be noticed by the emperor which
doesn't seem like a curse right it seems
like a blessing
to be noticed by someone in power seems
why would they think of that as a curse
but hold on hold on
the third one is may you be given the
position
you seek in the emperor in the imperial
palace
in other words me you have your cake you
get
everything you want which doesn't which
which seems like uh a shocking thing to
say to an activist of course that's what
we want we want to pull down the power
we want to over
uh run through the bastille and chase
out
the royals and all of that and behead
them you know
want to do all of that and install a
more just system
this curse is a pause is an invitation
to hesitate
about um moving forward
and and and so confidently that we
forget
that um sometimes we activate
in opposition we activate the very
premises
that gave birth to our incarceration let
me put it differently
that if you if you try to defeat
or gain a victory over your oppressors
within the epistemology
that is the condition for your
incarceration or your oppression
you risk reinforcing your oppression you
risk
reinforcing the dynamics of your
imprisonment
it's like what we know in africa we
chased away the british
we chased away uh the belgians we chased
away the french
we won but in a sense we lost
because immediately they they left we
pulled up our flags
and we started to play the game of
nation statism
we were already in the game and so even
though we won
we lost and so we tell ourselves that
even here in india
that if you win at your game you've lost
so this is the sense of the fugitive
that i want you to understand
defeat here is framed in pathological
terms in modernity
just like psychopathology um grieving is
bad i'm trained as a psychologist so i
know how to put people together
that's why we're called shrinks put them
back together put them back into the rat
race and let them be productive citizens
but there are spaces of power that might
be given
very fugitive mysterious names such as
defeat such as failure such as
poverty by the by the way guys i don't
know if you've
seen this news article that says um
the reason why it is a is hypothetical
that maybe the reason why people in
africa did not catch the virus as
much as people everywhere else is
because africa is poor
right that this is a new angle to
poverty
that vexes the notion of poverty as an
absolute evil and i'm not trying to
romanticize poverty here
but i'm trying to say that there is an
invitation that may be framed as defeat
uh that may be framed as failure but
it's an invitation to another place of
power altogether
okay um the french philosopher de luz
spoke about a politics of um
imperceptibility and a politics of
recognition
and i don't think he meant it as two
binary
um confrontational dynamics
i think there are places where they
intersect and they're places where they
break
from each other apologies of recognition
is about getting our voice out there
speaking truth to power
but there is a time when we can no
longer speak truth to power
right we can know we have to stop
speaking truth to power
um fred moulton i don't know if you guys
i don't know if he's been on this show
fred morton he wrote the book the under
commons
he speaks he says categorically one does
not
speak truth to power and i've wondered
about that statement
because in speaking truth to power we
often will reinforce
power we often will keep power
legitimate
so what do we do we fall away
and i'm not saying we do it wholesale
i'm not saying we replace the politics
of recognition
but at least we can supplement that um
instead of going to the shopping malls
there are communities in brazil that
have learned to use waste
as a form of wealth in the favelas so
they're not looking for handouts from
the government
if created an economy that is based on
the things that people throw away you
might think that's so distasteful
but i've been there and i've seen what
people are constructing
new technologies new experiments with
the normal
um so this is what i mean by defeat
that we need to unlearn our mastery
our sense of society and sovereignty
that gets in our heads so much that we
mess up everything
and finally brother just to end this
this part of the
response trump called my country
a [ __ ] country and
especially in nigeria nigeria is the
largest black
conglomeration of bodies on the planet
right so
he directed it in nigeria i hear and he
called it a [ __ ] that [ __ ]
country
and most nigerians i know where you know
we're furious
how dare you do that we have skyscrapers
we have
highways we have everything america has
right
how dare you call us you should home and
i think they missed the point
and i say that as a fugitive nigerian
living in india
that there is there is abundance in [ __ ]
you know and i feel there's a lot of
gift in shittiness um
that india the country i have adopted at
home
knows about that [ __ ] that which we
uh our marxist toilets takes away from
us
the productions of our bodies it takes
it away from us
you know there is without romanticizing
that there is um
the future isn't green it's brown
there's an invitation to stay with our
waste
uh to to look at the things that come
out of our bodies
not as things to be thrown away but as
you know as emblematic figures of the
future we're all walking towards
there's power there brother um so that's
what i mean by defeat
i mean a place of playfulness
improvisation
dance and fugitive possibilities thank
you bio that was amazing
thank you you're welcome brother thank
you
so we have about seven minutes left uh
do you have time for one more question
bio yeah yeah yeah i do i do i do
i do sorry i'm trying to install this uh
thing here go ahead
oh cheryl just left okay so um instead
of reading her question i'll ask one
cheryl's actually still here uh she just
had to disconnect from the call i'm in
the same room as her
oh does she wanna uh she there to read
uh her question yeah sure here i'll just
bring it over
[Music]
sorry i'm jumping on another meeting um
but i did have a question because
i'm really deeply everything that you're
saying
kind of strikes a chord in my heart that
feels so true and so resonant
especially in this journey that i've
really been on
in terms of unlearning a lot of the maps
that i've been giving
and trying to explore this kind of
territory of the unknown
i think something that i am curious
about though is
as i'm as i'm navigating
this very very dark mysterious i
i see it as a forest and i'm feeling it
through my hands and through my feet and
i feel like i'm using my intuition to
also know it
a fear that i hold is that i
will get lost in places that are
truly monstrous that are truly um
i think truly exploitative and truly um
kind of
will impact me in ways that um i'm
afraid of
so i think i'm i want to ask
what kind what is your recommendation or
what are your thoughts around the kind
of compass
i guess of the soul that we can build to
be able to navigate these spaces where
we can still be connected to i guess
what
what is true to ourselves through this
mysterious space
right right thank you so much sister
is that xavier is am i pronouncing that
right
oh yeah this is cheryl i'm cheryl i just
left the call
okay okay okay yeah yeah thank you thank
you
okay cheryl um oh that is such a that is
such a
necessary question to ask and i'm so
grateful that you
you have asked that um
but what comes to mind might seem like a
buddhist
diversion um from a direct response
and maybe what comes to mind right now
is is your life your own
do our lives belong to us
because if my life belongs to me then
it's um it's a poor life by default
it's poor because there's not much i can
do with it
um i like to think of myself
my life if i could speak of it in
very contractual terms or
property ownership terms i like to think
of it
as intergenerational that my
failure belongs to many kinds of bodies
not just human bodies but non-human
bodies i'm an animist at heart you know
a new materialist so my body is not mine
it's it's a part it belongs to a
parliament of beings
and voices and possibilities um
and that means um and i i probably don't
know why i'm
prefacing what i want to say with this
but it's probably necessary to say this
because
um the fears that we have about losing
our way
um or messing up
or strain into because strain is very
fearful business
especially when you're found and cuddled
and cradled in
modernity just stating in the womb of
modernity as we are
the invitation to become lost is
frightening
and even i speaking this to you it's
i don't know how that looks like every
time right
we can only approach it in modest ways
and the approach there's no arrival
sister there is only the approach
the approach is the sacred not the
arrival right
um so maybe the reason why i'm saying
this is
a bit of that fear might be alchemized
into curiosity or even
joy when we realized that our failure is
also part of how the world materializes
how the universe materializes that um
the shrinking away from the dark spaces
which were
mostly conditioned to behave you know
or to be like as modern citizens as
modern subjects
um shrinking away from animal alien
subjectivities
that is is a problem in itself
and and maybe the invitation to see
ourselves as large
as diffracted as widespread you know is
already answers that question in a way
and don't fear too much
in fact fear is a gift treat the fear
as an offering and treat it in the
company of others
find ways of listening to elders those
who have gone before
and those who know how to meet monsters
you know find them and listen to them if
you find them
great that's a gift you know those who
know how to listen to mountains and
listen to plants
you know we think of power and justice
today as majoritarian
bringing people from the hall the belly
of the slave ship
to the opera deck i think of justice in
terms of going to the hall
you know going to those places that are
deemed dark
and messy and sweltering and horrible
and that there is a gift there in
staying there
um so what i would say and if i were
in a different kind of conversation with
you i might train things differently but
because we're in company of others
i would just say that find the others
find those who might guide you
to meet those beasts right
and they might teach you
i i sense that the teachers of today
might teach you the teachers that are
rising
in these pandemic george floydian
moments
might might teach you that don't fear
those
monsters so much you know don't run away
from them
stay still stay still in front of them
because their agency and gift to you is
to remodel you
is to remember you in terms of
reconfiguring your body
is to prepare you and compost you for
new kinds of worlds
that even your failure your the
impossibility of arriving
is a gift to others that you may never
be able to see
or name so please find them um and they
will also find you i think we're seeking
each other right now
it's not just left up to you sister um
we're finding each other
ancestors are you know coming to the
surface
again like i say all the time when
worlds and
ancestors show up you know when worlds
and
ghosts show up ghosts are all over the
place if you will
um i think they're seeking us and they
will teach you what to do
because i don't know how to respond to
the specificities of your question i
feel there's something lingering there
but as you dwell in that space they will
find you
okay yeah thank you so much
and you you are one of those teachers
for me so
thank you thank you sister thank you
thank you that's um a beautiful note to
end on uh any any final words for us uh
before we
officially close out today
um anytime i see this my wife rules her
eyes off
or my colleagues roll their eye because
i say too much but i'm going to say it
again
the times are urgent let us slow down
the times are urgent let all slow down
the times are urgent let us slow
down i do not mean doing yoga in the
office
i do not mean taking a holiday i'm
talking about slowing down to listen
slowing down to notice the other
temporalities that are cross
intersecting or intersecting
the temporality of progress of moving
forward
you know they're they're blocking our
path and the place where the obstacle is
is where the treasure is
so let us sit around the treasure let us
sit around the obstacle let us treat the
rupture in the ground as a classroom
and and maybe by being there um
we might become different
amen so
in a moment i'll do some closing
announcements but bio thank you so much
for coming my friend that was very
beautiful
um i just i'm just filled with
excitement energy
dumos so thank you so much for visiting
the stoa today
thank you thank you very much thank you
am i to
go now exit left uh yeah you can
i'm just gonna make some closing
thoughts uh you can you can stay
i don't know how many you're closing you
can see how it's how weird we get here
at the stoa uh
so upcoming events uh tonight we have um
using street epistemology during culture
war
2.0 with anthony magna bosco a little
different than
what we just talked about today and then
that's at 6 00 pm eastern
time and after that at 10 pm eastern
time
uh jason fox had to be a meta modern
thought leader
uh you can rsvp there upcoming events on
the website
here's a discord the mailing list and if
you'd like to support us
on patreon you can do so at the website
we'd love to give you more events like
this
that being said bio thank you everyone
thank you for coming out today